<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life and death of Mr. Ignatius Jurdain, one  of the aldermen of the city of Exeter; who departed this life July 15th. 1640. Drawn up and published by Ferd. Nicolls, minister of the Gospel at Mary Arches, Exon.</title>
            <author>Nicolls, Ferdinando, 1598?-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1139</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E730_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206858</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865957</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865957</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118215</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89689)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E730[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life and death of Mr. Ignatius Jurdain, one  of the aldermen of the city of Exeter; who departed this life July 15th. 1640. Drawn up and published by Ferd. Nicolls, minister of the Gospel at Mary Arches, Exon.</title>
                  <author>Nicolls, Ferdinando, 1598?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Newberry, and are to be sold at his shop at the three Golden Lions on Corn-hill by the Royal Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654 [i.e. 1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 23:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jurdain, Ignatius, d. 1640 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>City council members --  England --  Exeter --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LIFE and DEATH OF Mr. Ignatius Jurdain, ONE OF THE Aldermen of the <hi>City of Exeter;</hi> Who departed this Life <hi>July</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1640.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 37.37.</bibl>
               <p>Mark the perfect man, and behold the upright; for the end of that man is peace.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 112.9.</bibl>
               <p>He hath diſperſed, he hath given to the poor, his righteouſneſſe endureth for ever.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 15.55.</bibl>
               <p>O death where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory?</p>
            </q>
            <p>Drawn up and publiſhed by <hi>Ferd. Nicolls,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Mary Arches, Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Newberry,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the three <hi>Golden Lions</hi> on Corn-hill by the Royal Exchange. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right VVorſhipfull <hi>Simon Snow</hi> Eſquire, <hi>Major</hi> of the <hi>City of Exeter,</hi> the <hi>Aldermen,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Common Councel</hi> of that <hi>City.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have had many <hi>thoughts</hi> heretofore, and ſome of late, to publiſh a ſhort <hi>Narrative</hi> of the Life, and Death of Mr. <hi>Ignatius Jurdain,</hi> a Worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your <hi>Society;</hi> and the latter might have been ſtifled as the former, had not the <hi>ſolicitations</hi> of ſome friends, both nearer and farther off, <hi>excited</hi> me to carry on my <hi>purpoſe</hi> to <hi>performance;</hi> And having ſet about this buſineſſe and brought it to ſome iſſue, I have taken the boldneſſe to preſent it unto you; and I ſuppoſed, that it would not be <hi>unacceptable</hi> to you, he being for a long time of your <hi>Society,</hi> and an <hi>honour</hi> thereunto as unto the whole <hi>City:</hi> His <hi>Name</hi> (no doubt) would have <hi>lived,</hi> and that in great eſteem, though this <hi>ſmall memorial</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:118215:3"/>him had never ſeen the light; but yet hereby many may take notice of more particulars, then formerly they have heard of, and take occaſion to recount many more <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable,</hi> and <hi>praiſe-worthy qualifications</hi> that were in him, then have come to my Knowledge: I might have added many more things, but I have omitted them, partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was not aſſured of the <hi>certainty</hi> of them, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe I declined <hi>Perſonal reflections,</hi> which would have ſounded very harſhly in the eares of many. That which hath been done (though with much weakneſſe, and not anſwerable to his worth) hath been out of a deſire to <hi>honour</hi> him, that was ſo <hi>zealous</hi> for the <hi>advancing of Gods glory,</hi> and to ſet his <hi>example</hi> before your ſelves, and others for <hi>imitation:</hi> For the good examples of holy men are as the <hi>light ſide of the cloud,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb. 12.1.</hi> Perk. in loc. N. Annot. in loc. Dyk. Dec. of the heart. c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> to give light to others, and to <hi>direct</hi> them in the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> of this World towards the <hi>heavenly Canaan.</hi> I know you have a <hi>ſurer and a ſtraighter rule, and a brighter light</hi> to direct you, then any <hi>humane examples,</hi> the <hi>infallible and unerring Word of God,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.105. Prov. 6.23.</note> Pſal. 119. &amp; Prov. 6. <hi>whereunto you ſhall do well to take heed as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19.</note> 2 Pet 1. But yet <hi>God</hi> himſelf would have us to obſerve the <hi>commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable examples</hi> of <hi>good men,</hi> and to ſet them before us for our <hi>imitation and pattern,</hi> as<note n="(d)" place="margin">Prov. 2.20.</note> Prov. 2. <hi>To walk in the way of good men,</hi> and <hi>to be followers, or imitators of them,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 Cor 4. but we may not follow the beſt of men in all things but with a limitation, as they follow that <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Rule Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1.</note> 1 Cor. 11. And I know not, whether I ſhould preſſe the imitation of this <hi>renowned Worthy,</hi> in all things, as in his ſo early riſing in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to <hi>enjoy communion</hi> with <hi>God</hi> in <hi>holy meditation,</hi> the bodily temper of moſt not being able to bear it, ſo that we may herein rather <hi>admire</hi> then <hi>imitate</hi> him. He was
<pb facs="tcp:118215:3"/>(as I conceive) of an <hi>Heroical and raiſed ſpirit,</hi> elevated above the<note n="*" place="margin">Abſit verbo invidia.</note> ordinary rank of true Profeſſours of Reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion; for as <hi>Heroical vertue</hi> (as the Moraliſts<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ariſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thic. lib. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Piccol. Philoſ. Grad. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi>—<hi>6.</hi>
               </note> ſay) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells <hi>moral vertue</hi> in an <hi>high and eminent</hi> degree; ſo there is a kind of <hi>Heroical</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Keck. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. Eth. lib.;. c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſpiritual vertue,</hi> as <hi>Abrahams Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency in Faith,</hi> and the like I may ſay of this <hi>Holy mans intenſiveneſs</hi> in zeale for <hi>God,</hi> that excels the ordinary <hi>vertue</hi> of Chriſtians.<note place="margin">(i) <hi>2 Pet. 1.3.</hi> Called to glory and vertue.</note> I know that ſome did much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue him, as a man of meane and low parts; they would acknowledge, that he was an honeſt well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, but weake, and beneath thoſe that were accounted wiſe men; but ſuppoſe that his naturall, and acquired parts were not ſo great as ſome others, yet for his <hi>zeale and courage</hi> for the <hi>truth and cauſe of God,</hi> his <hi>cloſe communion</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>indignation againſt ſin,</hi> I dare boldly ſay, he did excell the moſt of men: And they that have greater parts of <hi>knowledge and wiſedome,</hi> ſhould be provoked by his example, to act the more <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly</hi> for God, for every man muſt give an account of the <hi>improving</hi> his <hi>talents</hi> for the<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mat. 25.15.</note> behoof of the <hi>Lord,</hi> that hath intruſted them therewith, remembring that of our <hi>Saviour</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>To whom much is given, of him ſhall much be required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be <hi>three things,</hi> which in the enſuing <hi>Narrative,</hi> you ſhall find very <hi>commendable</hi> in him; his <hi>Piety, Juſtice and Charity,</hi> wherein I ſhall crave leave to commend him to your <hi>imitation,</hi> and if you ſhall exceed him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I know no good man that will blame you, though I cannot ſecure you from the <hi>Scorpion like laſh</hi> of the <hi>viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent tongues</hi> of wicked men.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For his <hi>Piety,</hi> all that knew him, and did not look upon him with an <hi>evill eye,</hi> will give teſtimony to it; and it will be your <hi>honour</hi> to ſtand up zealouſly for <hi>God,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118215:4"/>and to <hi>walk ſincerely and uprightly before him,</hi> and as <hi>under his eye,</hi> who <hi>ſeeth</hi> not only all your <hi>actions,</hi> but your ſeeret <hi>intents, purpoſes and deſigns,</hi> whether you look with <hi>a ſquint-eye</hi> upon your <hi>ſiniſter &amp; ſelf-ends,</hi> or with a <hi>ſingle eye aime at his glory,</hi> in all your <hi>undertakings:</hi> And you ſhould let it appeare, that you are on the <hi>Lords-ſide,</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Exod. 32.26.</note> now ſo many <hi>Apoſtat ſe and revolt,</hi> yea, <hi>deeply</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Eſay 31.6.</note> 
               <hi>revolt from him,</hi> I ſpeak it not in way of doubt or jealouſie of you, for many <hi>bleſſe God</hi> for your <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs in the faith,</hi> in theſe declining dayes; and your <hi>conſtant attending</hi> upon the <hi>Lords holy Ordinances</hi> both on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> and <hi>Week dayes</hi> is very <hi>exemplary,</hi> not onely to thoſe of inferiour rank in this <hi>City,</hi> but to others that either ſee, or hear of your <hi>forwardneſſe</hi> therein. But <hi>Holineſſe</hi> ſhould appear alſo in the <hi>whole courſe</hi> of your <hi>converſation,</hi> both in your <hi>publike adminiſtrations of Juſtice,</hi> (for <hi>you judge not for man but for the Lord,</hi> 2 Chron. 19.<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Chr. 19.6.</note> And the <hi>Seat of Juſtice</hi> is the <hi>place of the Holy,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. 8.10.</hi> N. Annot. in loc. Pemb. Expoſ.</note> the <hi>Holy One, or Holy God;</hi>) and in your more <hi>private converſing</hi> with men, and moſt <hi>ſecret retirements, Holineſſe to the Lord,</hi> that under the Law was <hi>engraven</hi> upon the <hi>High Prieſts Miter,</hi> and to be <hi>worn upon his forehead,</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">Exod. 28.36.</note> Exod. 28. ſhould now be written on <hi>things of common uſe,</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech. 14.20.</hi> N. Annot. in loc.</note> Zech. 14. you ſhould <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate</hi> your ſelves and all your actions to the <hi>ſervice of</hi> the <hi>Holy God;</hi> the more <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>conſtant</hi> you are herein, with the greater <hi>comfort</hi> you will give up your <hi>account</hi> unto the <hi>righteous Judge,</hi> when you ſhall be called unto it; and your <hi>account</hi> drawes very nigh, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.<note n="(s)" place="margin">Jam. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>Behold the Judge ſtandeth before the door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. His <hi>impartial adminiſtration of Juſtice</hi> againſt Swearers, open profaners of the Sabbath, unclean per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and other ſcandalous Offenders wherein he ſhewed himſelf another<note n="(t)" place="margin">N h. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 106.30.</note> 
               <hi>Phinehas,</hi> will but
<pb facs="tcp:118215:4"/>mind you of that, which I have cauſe to be perſwaded, that you reſolve to do; And you have <hi>advantage</hi> to do more, in ſome reſpects, then he had, becauſe many of thoſe diſorders and <hi>pollutions</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Eſay 56. 2-6.</note> of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> (the removing of which found great reſiſtance in thoſe daies) have been, for many years, taken away, and yet I dare not ſay that he was the <hi>firſt</hi> that brake the ice, and ſet upon the <hi>reformation</hi> of abuſes upon the <hi>Lords holy day;</hi> for I am informed by one, that was an <hi>Active Officer</hi> in the redreſſing of thoſe profane abuſes, that his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> John Sheere, <hi>Major.</hi> A.D. <hi>1616.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Predeceſſour</hi> in the <hi>Office</hi> of the <hi>Majoralty</hi> did <hi>begin</hi> to <hi>reform</hi> ſome open <hi>profanations of the Sabbath;</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any did attempt it before, is more then I can learn, it being long before my coming to the <hi>City.</hi> But <hi>God</hi> hath a <hi>perfect Record</hi> of all things that are done by men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for his <hi>names ſake,</hi> whether men take notice of it or no.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. And for his <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>beneficence</hi> to the <hi>poor</hi> and other <hi>pious uſes;</hi> I leave it to your ſerious conſideration, how far he was a <hi>pattern</hi> to you therein, if you think it too much to do as much as he did, yet <hi>liberality</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe</hi> in well-doing is left as a <hi>charge</hi> upon you by <hi>God</hi> himſelf,<note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17, 18.</note> 1 Tim. 6. and <hi>he would not have you to forget it,</hi> Heb. 13.<note n="(y)" place="margin">Heb. 13.16.</note> ſeeing it is <hi>well-pleaſing</hi> to him; And you will be <hi>no loſers</hi> by it <hi>here</hi> but <hi>great gainers;</hi> the more <hi>free</hi> you are this way, you may expect that the <hi>Lord</hi> will deal the more <hi>freely,</hi> and <hi>bountifully</hi> with you, or yours, you have his <hi>Word,</hi> and that's as good as any <hi>bond</hi> for you.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Prov. 11.24 25. Eccleſ. 11.1— Pſal. 37.26. Eſay. 32.8.</note> ſee Prov. 11. Eccleſ. 11. Pſal. 37. and Eſay 32. And this will <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rther your account,</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Phil. 4.17.</note> Phil. 4. in the <hi>great day</hi> of <hi>reckoning,</hi> for then the Lord will take ſpecial notice, not ſo much, of that which you have <hi>laid up</hi> for your ſelves, or yours, as of that, which you have
<pb facs="tcp:118215:5"/>
               <hi>laid out</hi> for him, and his. But I am here prevented in preſſing one point of <hi>Charity</hi> upon you, for providing for the poor; for in your late act of <hi>Charity,</hi> ſhall I tearm it? or <hi>Juſtice and Mercy meeting together,</hi> I mean the erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Work houſe:</hi> You have taken the beſt care that the ranging and diſorderly poor might be ſet on work, and ſo be better provided for by their <hi>own labour,</hi> then by being <hi>relieved</hi> at mens doors; and <hi>that no</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 144.14.</note> 
               <hi>complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> by that clamorous ſort of idle people, may, for the future, <hi>be heard in our ſtreets.</hi> The Lord ſtrengthen your hearts and hands for the perfecting of that <hi>righteous and charitable work,</hi> and for the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 41.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Piſc. Qui pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter ſegerit. Gen.</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Judgeth wiſely. <hi>Ainſw.</hi> Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</note> 
               <hi>wiſe conſidering</hi> the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the impotent <hi>poor,</hi> that they being reſtrained from begging, may have no juſt cauſe of <hi>complaining</hi> to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>man</hi> by reaſon of <hi>want. God</hi> hath <hi>honoured you</hi> above many, I beſeech you let it be your chiefeſt care to <hi>honour him,</hi> in the faithful diſcharge of your <hi>duty</hi> unto him, and of the <hi>truſt</hi> committed by him unto you, that this <hi>City</hi> may be truly ſtiled <hi>the faithful City,</hi> Eſay 1.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eſay 1.26. <hi>Fidelis in aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> The City's Motto.</note> and we may ſay with the Prophet, Jer. 31.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Jer. 31.23.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee thou habitation of Juſtice and mountain of holineſſe;</hi> This is the ſincere deſire of him that is willing to ſign himſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sirs, <hi>Yours to be Commanded in the ſervice of the Goſpel,</hi> Ferdinando Nicolls.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Exon.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 24. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> The READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a truth which alwaies God hath made good in his providence, <hi>that the memorial of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed;</hi> therefore ſince the <hi>Canon</hi> and rule of faith, or thoſe Authentick records which we call <hi>The Scriptures,</hi> have been cloſed up: The Lord hath ſtirred up in every age ſome that could <hi>handle the pen of the writer,</hi> to continue the memory of his eminent and faithful ſervants to poſterity with praiſe and honour. It would be vain in a caſe ſo known, to tell you particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly what hath been done in this kind, by <hi>Dorotheus, Sophronius, Jerome, Gennadius, Epiphanius,</hi> &amp;c. and by modern Writers without number; the Ancient Church had her <hi>Diptychs</hi> or publick Tables, wherein the names of perſons moſt noted for piety were recorded; and though the modern <hi>Canonization</hi> uſed among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118215:6"/>be ridiculous, and ſome <hi>Sainted</hi> that were<note n="*" place="margin">Hominum monſira—heu quam multi inter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines Scripti ſunt in Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum albo qui in arcano dei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilio deſcripti ſunt in reprobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nigro: quam multi ſunt ac quorum imagines ardent cereis, qui ipſi ardent in flamma! <hi>Molinaei Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraſpiſtes.</hi> pag. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> ſcarce <hi>men,</hi> and their <hi>legends</hi> bundles of lyes the very ſtain and infamy of Chriſtianity; yet there is no reaſon that the true Saints, <hi>Gods Worthies,</hi> ſhould be defrauded of their publick honour, and buried in obſcurity and ſilence without any Monument of their worth, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious eminency: eſpecially when we do conſider how much <hi>Gods glory</hi> is concerned in the credit of his ſervants, as alſo the <hi>profit</hi> of others; partly that they may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the ancient wayes of the Spirit, and thoſe <hi>Good old pathes</hi> wherein the Children of God walked and enjoyed communion with him: partly that they may be provoked by their examples to follow them in <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>patience,</hi> and <hi>heavenlineſſe</hi> and <hi>ſtrictneſſe</hi> of converſation; we ſee many times that <hi>examples</hi> work more then <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> not onely as they <hi>convince,</hi> but as they do <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage:</hi> they convince more, becauſe they are <hi>real,</hi> we look upon <hi>precepts</hi> as <hi>words</hi> ſpoken of courſe, wherein Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may be counterfeited at a cheaper rate; therefore <hi>Noah,</hi> though <hi>a Preacher of righteouſneſſe,</hi> is ſaid to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the world by <hi>preparing An Ark,</hi> Heb. 11.8. and <hi>they incourage,</hi> becauſe in them we ſee, that the exerciſe of <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> though <hi>difficult,</hi> yet is <hi>poſsible,</hi> when men that are <hi>ſubject to like paſsions,</hi> and have the ſame intereſts and Concernments of fleſh and blood that we have, can be thus <hi>mortified, ſelf-denying, heavenly, holy:</hi> now <hi>examples</hi> have this force, not onely when the Saints are <hi>alive,</hi> and liable to preſent notice and obſervation, but <hi>after their death,</hi> when tranſmitted to poſterity by faithful records; yea then many times they work more, their infirmities being buried with them, and their lives do then rather <hi>inſtruct</hi> then <hi>Exaſperate,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Paſcitur in Vivis livor, poſt fata qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſcit.</note> living Saints ſtanding in the way of intereſts are more hated, and looked upon with
<pb facs="tcp:118215:6"/>prejudice, but uſually there is a greater eſteem of the dead; how often do Gods Children live <hi>envied,</hi> and die <hi>Sainted!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this is prefaced <hi>(Reader)</hi> to induce thee to a more ſerious conſideration of the preſent memorials of that holy man, Mr. <hi>Ignatius Jurdain,</hi> in ſome ſenſe, <hi>the Wonder and Phoenix of his Age and place of abode;</hi> concerning whoſe <hi>piety</hi> and frequent communion with God, his <hi>conſtant heavenlineſſe,</hi> his <hi>charity</hi> in <hi>giving, lending,</hi> and <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining,</hi> his <hi>doing juſtice</hi> with <hi>impartiality</hi> and <hi>diligence,</hi> thou wilt have a more particular account in the enſuing ſtory; only give me leave from my ſelf to ſuggeſt a few paſſages and obſervations: 1. That for his temper he was a man of <hi>a raiſed Zeal</hi> and <hi>Heroical ſpirit,</hi> one of thoſe <hi>rare examples</hi> which the Lord giveth the World now and then, and therefore his actions are not to be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by an ordinary ſtandard. 2. Seldom or never did any come into his company, but he would diſcourſe with them about holy things, asking the younger <hi>how they ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to be ſaved?</hi> the more grown if they profeſſed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>whether they had any aſſurance?</hi> which if they denyed, he would tell them that <hi>he was even aſhamed of them; in good earnest</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I would ſtudy the promiſes, and go into my cloſet and lock, the door, and there plead them to God, and ſay, that I would not go forth till he gave me ſome ſence of his love.</hi> 3. His entertainment at his Table was <hi>free</hi> and <hi>ſufficient,</hi> but <hi>frugal</hi> and <hi>ſober;</hi> if his Wife at any time excuſed the ſlenderneſſe of it, he would ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">Humilis cibus &amp; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nius potus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt divitiae Chriſtianorum, Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>Brown bread and Kennel water is good fare with the Goſpel.</hi> I have often heard him ſay ſo, there is ſomewhat a like ſaying of Mr. <hi>Greenham's,</hi> and poſſibly Mr. <hi>Jurdain</hi> might bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row it thence, it ſuiting ſo well with the temper of his ſpirit. 4. <hi>A formal man</hi> had once preached a Sermon
<pb facs="tcp:118215:7"/>at the Cathedral about <hi>heaven,</hi> the diſcourſe was for the moſt part <hi>frothy,</hi> and beneath the dignity and worth of ſuch an argument, Mr. <hi>Jurdain</hi> was preſent as well as my ſelf, after Sermon I went to his houſe, (being to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Letter from him for <hi>Oxford</hi>) after many good inſtructions he asked me, <hi>if I had been at the Sermon that morning?</hi> I told him, yea; and <hi>did you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hear thoſe wonderful things which God hath provided for them that love him?</hi> and ſo readily picked out all thoſe paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which were any way ſubſervient to uſe and profit; 'twas wonderful to me, to ſee how an holy heart can draw comfort out of any thing: the Sermon as <hi>Mr. Jur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain</hi> repeated it to me, was another kind of Sermon, and ſeemed to be very ſavoury and ſpiritual: I remember with what warmth and vigour he ſpake of it, even to this day, and hope that I never ſhall forget it. 5. This is not to be forgotten, his ſending a Letter to the <hi>late King,</hi> and expoſtulating with him about his ſetting forth the Book concerning ſports and recreations on the Lords day, which was incloſed in another to the Biſhop of <hi>Exeter,</hi> to deſire him to convey it: and notice being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Biſhop that Copies of it were divulged (poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly by the tranſcriber) he thought he could not conceal it with ſafety, and therefore carried it to the King, who when he had read it, in a great Anger ſaid <hi>he would hang him;</hi> But the Biſhop (a pious man) fell upon his knees, and beſought his Majeſties pardon, alledging, <hi>That God had not a better ſervant, nor his Majeſtie a better Subject in the whole Land:</hi> When the Biſhop returned from his moneth of attendance, <hi>Mr. Jurdain</hi> went to viſit him, and after civilities paſt, the Biſhop ſaid, <hi>Ah Mr. Jurdain would you put me upon ſo hot a ſervice? you know there are many eyes upon me:</hi> (meaning the Archbiſhops faction, who
<pb facs="tcp:118215:7"/>ſuſpected him as a favourer of <hi>Puritans</hi>) <hi>Yea my Lord</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed M <hi>Jurdain</hi>) <hi>there are eyes upon you, the eyes of God and his holy Angels to ſee how you diſcharge your Office and Duty as the Kings Chaplain and a Biſhop of the Church.</hi> 6. Now and then, when he had leiſure, he would often go to his neighbours ſhops, and admoniſh them to take heed that the cares of the World did not deadden their ſpirits to heavenly things, telling them, <hi>If they had many thouſands it would not ſtill the cry of conſcience, purchaſe the leaſt fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from God, not ſo much as eaſe the pain of the teeth, or keep off one fit of an ague, yea if mony were thrown to the dogs they would not ſo much as ſmell at it.</hi> 7. He would often per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade his fellow-Magiſtrates to a liberal proviſion for the poor: and when they would ask him <hi>where they ſhould have money?</hi> he would Anſwer, <hi>God will provide, rather then the poor ſhall want let us ſell our Gownes.</hi> 8. When he diſtributed money to the poor with his own hands in a time of great infection, and ſo ſome asked him if he were not afraid of the plague, <hi>What</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>afraid of Gods vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation! let us fear rather the plague ſore of our own heart.</hi> 9. In his troubles in the Star-Chamber, when one told him, he was ſorry the <hi>Lord-Keeper</hi> was againſt him, he Anſwered, <hi>I have a greater Lord-Keeper then him, the Lord is my keeper, I ſhall not be afraid.</hi> 10. 'Tis not amiſſe to obſerve what others thought and ſaid of him; I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber a godly man obſerves of him, <hi>that in every buſineſſe</hi> (though in ſome he adventured far) <hi>the Lord carried him thorough with reputation,</hi> and ſo compares him with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of great parts, who though godly was alwaies foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in every undertaking: Drunkards and frequenters of the Ale-houſe were afraid of him, he was their <hi>uſual bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear;</hi> their <hi>Memento</hi> in the middle of their exceſſe was, <hi>It is time to be gone, Mr. Jurdain will come by and by:</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:118215:8"/>ordinary ſort of men were convinced of his integrity: I have over-heard men carnal and vitious at a time of election of Burgeſſes for the Parliament, ſpeaking to one another, <hi>if you chooſe any chooſe Jurdain, he will be right for the Common Wealth, and do the City ſe vice:</hi> he was twice choſen Burgeſſe for the Parliament, and twice Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor of the City, and once Deputy Major in a time of great infection and peſtilence: The reverend Miniſter that preached his Funeral Sermon (from whom you have the diſcourſe of his life) ſaid, <hi>Look upon his Will, and you will think him the richeſt man in this City;</hi> though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny exceeded him in eſtate, but few or none in making proviſion for the poor; delinquents ſeldome went from him without conviction: A Noblemans ſervant that had ſcorned him being brought before him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of having ſworn raſhly three times, Mr. <hi>Jurdain</hi> demanded his Fine, and ſhewed him the hainouſneſſe of the ſin, with which the man was calmed, and though he came from his Companions braving, yet he returned with the acknowledgment that he was a <hi>faithfull Juſticer,</hi> and when they asked him what <hi>Jurdain</hi> did to him, he Anſwered, <hi>he gave me good Law, and fair words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good Reader, by this taſte thou mayeſt judge of the Man, thou wilt be better acquainted with him, when thou haſt read over the enſuing Collection of the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his life, drawn up by an able and faithful hand, who hath been carefull that nothing ſhould be inſerted of which he had not ſufficient evidence, and that many things might be omitted which could not be divulged without reflection on particular perſons; whatever is lacking of conſequence may be ſupplyed in another Edition.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:8"/>
            <p>Thus much I thought good to ſignifie to thee, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Lord to help us more and more to be followers of them <hi>who through faith and patience have inherited the promiſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the ſervice of the Goſpel, <hi>Thomas Manton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata to be corrected.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. line the laſt, for [Or] read [and] p. 3. l. 11. I intend [not] to be inſerted, l. 22. Gen. 9.5. figure 9. to be blotted out. line 30 Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious prefixe (a) ret. line 31 for [that] read [if] page 4. line 1 for [which] read [with] line 7. for [if he] inſert [as] line 16. Rom. 7. the next figure to be blotted out. page 5. l. 18. He had taken, dele [taken] pag 6. Marg. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 8. l. 17. for [free] r. [frequent] p. 9. l penult marg. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 13 l 20. for [fully] read [wholly] page 14. l. 10. for [Duy] r. [duty] p 18. line 30 was choſen, r. twice choſen. p 19. line 11 dele [and reproved by his holy and gracious converſation,] it being twice printed, line 18. Marg. Act. 5.4. read 41.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118215:9"/>
            <head>The Life and Death of M. <hi>Ignatius Jurdain</hi> one of the Aldermen of the City of <hi>Exeter,</hi> who died <hi>July</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1640.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>memory of the juſt is bleſſed,</hi> ſaith wiſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon Prov.</hi> 10.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Prov. 10.7.</note> he leaves a ſweet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial behind him, though, whileſt he lived, he was vilified and defamed, and loaden with reproaches, yet when he is departed this life, his name is as a ſweet and precious Oyntment, even unto thoſe that formerly could take up his name as a Proverbe of reproach, but eſpecially to thoſe that honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in life and death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His memorial is bleſſed.</note>This <hi>Eminent Saint, this holy and juſt Man</hi> is a Real proof of that doctrinal Aſſertion of <hi>Solomon; his memoral is bleſſed,</hi> and they that in his life time undervalued him, do now (or ſeem at leaſt to) make an Honourable mention of him; but he now lives with much honour in the hearts of thoſe that ſaw and acknowledged that true worth which was in him, when he was deſpiſed by the men of the World; but there may <hi>a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ariſe which knew him not,</hi> and that which hath been received by tradition may be forgotten. That therefore his name may live, when others, that maligned him, dye, or their names rot,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118215:10"/>and that he may be a pattern of Piety and Charity to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding generations, it hath been thought fit to commit to writing, and to publiſh to the world thoſe ſingular graces, and memorable acts that did ſhine forth in him both living and dying; And it is not unworthy our obſervation, that God ſtirred up the ſpirits of divers well affected Chriſtians about one and the ſame time, to deſire the publiſhing of the Life of this <hi>renowned Worthy of the Lord,</hi> whom ſome may <hi>Envy,</hi> and others <hi>Emulate,</hi> but few are found that in all things do or can <hi>imitate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The place of his Birth.</note>
               <hi>Ignatius Jurdain</hi> was born at <hi>Lyme-Regis in the County of Dorſet,</hi> (that little Town ſo famous for the long Siege by the Kings forces, and for repelling the moſt furious aſſaults of thoſe that beleaguered it,) and it may add to the fame of it, that <hi>this man was born in her;</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 87.5. As it was an honour to be born in <hi>Zion,</hi> ſo it was an honour to <hi>Lyme</hi> that he was born there.</note> He was ſent by his Friends to <hi>Exeter</hi> when he was young, where he was to be brought up in the profeſſion of a Merchant; and being ſent to the <hi>Ile of Garnſey</hi> about the age of fifteen years, God, who by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence brought him to that Place, did by his Grace effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally call and Convert him; So that for after time he reſolved to be like that <hi>wiſe Merchant in the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Math. 13.46.</note> 
               <hi>to part with all for that Pearl of great Price,</hi> when many others did make it their great work and their higheſt deſign, to get the pelfe of the World, and to load <hi>themſelves with thick clay d.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hab. 2.6.</note> And in teſtimony of his thankfulneſſe to God, he left by Will a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Legacy to the Poor of <hi>Lyme,</hi> where he was born, and to the Poor of <hi>Garnſey</hi> where he was New-born.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in his younger years.</note>God ſeaſoning his heart with Grace in his younger years, the General courſe of his life did for the future relliſh of it, as <hi>wiſe Solomon hath obſerved</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov. 22.6.</hi> Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens Horat. Quintil: Jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit: Or at. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1. His Private Life.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. in the general, and in him we have a particular and approved inſtance. As he was trained up in Religion from his youth, ſo he continued, not only in the <hi>form and profeſſion,</hi> but in <hi>the Life and power of it,</hi> untill his old age, and death.</p>
            <p>What was more ſpecially worthy obſervation in his private courſe, before the time of ſhewing himſelf in his publick Office of Magiſtracy, I cannot give any certain account, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo long ſince; and there being but few living, that either did obſerve his holy converſation, or that are able and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118215:10"/>to give deſerved teſtimony to it; Few things are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of John (Baptiſt untill the <hi>day of his ſhewing unto Iſrael,</hi> viz. in his publick Miniſtery, Luke. 1.<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke 1.80.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Spanh. Dub. Eu. T. <hi>2.</hi> Dub. <hi>100.</hi>
               </note> And but little of our bleſſed Saviour himſelf until the time of his publick miniſtery. And therefore it is the more excuſable, if the former part of his life be paſſed over, and we come to the time when he was Magiſtrate, and the chiefeſt Magiſtrate, the Major of the City; I know not whether the City did more honour him in chuſing him to be Major, or he the City in his zealous and faithful diſcharge of his office and publick truſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Publike life in his Magiſtracy.</note>But I intend to limit my relation to his Acts and doings as a Magiſtrate (yet therein he was moſt exemplary to all that ſucceeded in that place of dignity, or the like in any other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Corporation) but ſhall declare that which hath been partly obſerved and teſtified by men of known Fidelity<note n="*" place="margin">Teſtes fide digni.</note> and Integrity, and partly noted by mine own experience and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; which that I may the more diſtinctly record, I ſhall refer all to three heads, his <hi>Piety, Juſtice and Charity,</hi> ſhewing how he honoured God therein; and then how God honoured &amp; preſerved him, when he was about his work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with his <hi>Piety,</hi> wherein he was moſt eminent; there have been few men obſerved <hi>to walk ſo with God as Enoch.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. His Piety.</note> Gen. 9.5. and <hi>before him,</hi> as it was enjoined to Abraham, Gen 17. and to hold ſo <hi>conſtant and cloſe communion</hi> with him as he did. It was his conſtant practiſe,<note n="(g)" place="margin">Gen. 5.22. Chap. 17.1.</note> for many years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether even to his old age, to ariſe betwixt two and three of the clock in the morning, and that in the coldeſt ſeaſon of the year, and then to meditate and pray in ſecret until ſixe a clock, the appointed time of the morning Sacrifice in the family; when he was called from ſecret devotions to the exerciſe of religious family-duties (rare and unparalled example of all that I have known or heard of;) And that at any time he had overſlept himſelf (as he accounted) and did not riſe untill four a clock, he would much bemone himſelf for that he had loſt ſo much time of ſweet and comfortable communion with God. And had he not experimentally found much ſweetneſs in this his ſpiritual converſe with God as David did,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 104.34.</note> Pſal. 104. he could not have continued ſo conſtant therein; And he thus awaking with God and renewing his acquaintance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118215:11"/>with him from day to day, no marvaile that he did walke whith him all the day long.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Sincerity.</note>His care was to <hi>walk very exactly and ſincerely</hi> according to the Apoſtles direction<note n="(i)" place="margin">Eph. 5.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> See Dr. <hi>Proſtons</hi> Sermon on that Text.</note> Eph. 5. but though he ſtudied to approve himſelf to God, and <hi>to walk as in the ſight of God</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">2 Cor. 2.17.</note> 2. Cor 2. yet he could not eſcape the malicious cenſures of men, if he did all in Hypocriſie; he knew that he had the imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of diſſembling and hypocriſy caſt upon him (by men void of charity and ſincerity) but the <hi>teſtimony of his own conſcience</hi> did more comfort him, then the <hi>uncharitable cenſures</hi> of men deject him, and he had wont, upon that occaſion, to take up the words of Job Chap 27.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Job 27.5.</note> 
               <hi>Till I die I will not remove mine integrity from me;</hi> and many have often heard him to profeſſe, that he would not willingly ſin to get a world, though <hi>the evil which he</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Rom. 7.25. His ſincerity queſtioned.</note> 
               <hi>would not do that he did,</hi> (as it is incident to the beſt of men Rom. 7.1. and he did bewail it with griefe of heart. The <hi>ſincerity hoth of his intentions and actions</hi> have been queſtioned, and ſome have not been aſhamed to ſay, that under colour of doing juſtice and providing for the poor, he robbed the poore, and helped to keep his own houſe with that mony, which was due to the poore. But for that falſhood which was charged upon him, there's none could ever better clear him from it then himſelf, not only his <hi>conſcience witneſſing for him before God,</hi> but his books (wherein he kept an exact record of the mony which he received for ſwearing and drunkenneſſe according to the penaltie of the law) and the Officers that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed the mony teſtifying <hi>his uprightneſſe</hi> before men; ſo that he might truly ſay with Jacob, Gen. 30.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Gen. 30.33.</note> 
               <hi>My righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſhall anſwer for me,</hi> and ſo it did herein both before God and men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the exerciſes of Religion.</note>He was a man that made <hi>Conſcience of all exerciſes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> both in private and publick, his frequent diſcourſes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the way thereunto, and aſſurance of intereſt therein, did declare, that his <hi>heart and converſation were much in heaven.</hi> Matt. 12.<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat. 12.34, 35.</note> And he had wont to take occaſion to confer of ſpiritual and heavenly things with all ſorts of men that he did converſe with; One ſhould ſeldom hear him ſpeak <hi>but of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and heavenly things,</hi> his heart was ſo full of heaven, that he could not but utter and breath it forth in his diſcourſes with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118215:11"/>men, and eſpecially with thoſe whoſe hearts and faces were towards heaven, when he was at Table receiving his daily food, he did uſually <hi>miniſter occaſion of holy diſcourſe,</hi> &amp; divert vain and unprofitable talke, to edifying ſpeeches that might <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter grace to the hearers</hi> Eph. 4.<note n="(p)" place="margin">Eph. 4.29.</note> and to take <hi>occaſion from earthly things to ſpeake of heavenly,</hi> as from the ſweetneſſe of the Creatures to ſpeak of the infinite ſweetneſſe which is in God, from feaſting on earth to the <hi>ſitting down with Abraham</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">Mat. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac and Jacob in the Kingdom of heaven,</hi> and feaſting with God and his bleſſed Saints there, and when the Table-cloth was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, he would often ſay <hi>[In heaven there's no taking away, here we are ſoon ſatisfied and cloyed, but there will be ſuch a feaſh that we ſhall be continually delighting our ſouls in it, without any cloying].</hi> And his manner was to cloſe his meales with the ſinging of ſome ſhort Pſalm.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Reading good Books.</note>He delighted much in reading <hi>good and holy books,</hi> but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the <hi>Book of books the holy Scriptures,</hi> wherein he moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted, he had taken therein the property <hi>of a godly perſon</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal. 1.2. Pſal. 119.97.</note> Pſ. 1. and Pſa, 119. <hi>The word of God was his meditation all the day long;</hi> yea day and night, he did <hi>not onely read the ſcripture more then twenty times over, but he read it with ſpecial obſervation</hi> (as appeareth by the<note n="*" place="margin">Starres in the margent. <hi>S. Senenſ. Bibl. l.</hi> 3. or ſuch like ſignal notes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> aſterisks and markes in his Bible) and application to himſelf. The like courſe he took in reading over that <hi>uſeful book of Mr. Rogers his ſeven Treatiſes,</hi> and other practical bookes wherein he was very converſant; and his collections out of ſeverall Authors do abundantly teſtifie; And he took ſo much delight in reading that <hi>voluminous and excellent book of the Acts and monuments of the Church, ſet forth by Mr. Foxe, commonly called the book of Maertyrs,</hi> that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occcaſion, he told a Friend, that he had read it ſeven times over.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Zeal.</note>His <hi>zeal for God and his glory,</hi> and againſt Idolatry, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe and other evils, whereby God was moſt highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, was moſt eminent and remarkable. He was a man of an <hi>Antilaodicean</hi> temper; he had well Learned the Apoſtles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.<note n="(s)" place="margin">Rom. 12.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as in ſome Copies.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>To be fervent in Spirit, ſerving the Lord, and not the time.</hi> He was not like another<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ignatius Ioiola</hi> the founder of the Order of the Jeſuites. <hi>Camerar. Hiſt. Obſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118215:12"/>was a man of fire, that was ſet on fire of hell to promote the cauſe of the Prince of darkneſſe; but he had an holy fire kindled in his heart from heaven, whereby he did burn with zeal for the advancing of Gods glory, and an holy indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt ſin and error; he would (if it had been poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) have burned up all the droſſe and filth, that did cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the truth of God, and was contrary to the way of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And therein he was very like unto<note n="u" place="margin">Euſeb: Hiſt. Eccl. l. 3. c. 30. Hiſt. Magdeb. Cent. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10. Fox's Acts &amp; Monuments in the 3. of the Ten Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions. He was a ſtrict obſerver of the Sabbath.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius the Martyr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was a <hi>very ſtrict and conſciencious obſerver of the Chriſtian Sabbath, the Lords day;</hi> He did then riſe very early as on other dayes (if not earlier) and did ſtir up thoſe of his family to an early riſing on that day, ſaying <hi>This is Gods day, and as we do expect that our ſervants ſhould riſe early to go about our work on our dayes, ſo God expects our early riſing on his day, to go about his work and ſervice]</hi> And he did then very carefully attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords holy Ordinances; the <hi>feet of them that diſpenced the Goſpel were very beautiful in his eyes.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. more beautifull then their faces to many others; he was one of thoſe <hi>Saints that ſate down at Gods feet to receive his Word</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 33.3. Act. 22.3. Chap. 21.16. <hi>Seneſco ſemper aliquid addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcens.</hi>
               </note> Deut. 33. <hi>as Diſciples at the feet of their teacher</hi> Act. 22. and he was very deſirous and willing to learn of any that came with the Lords meſſage unto him; he was <hi>a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſon, an old Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple Act.</hi> 21. A Diſciple when he was old; <hi>it never entred into his heart to cast off: Ordinances,</hi> no not when he had attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an high degree of Perfection; He was <hi>a conſtant noter of Sermons,</hi> even when he was old, not for his own benefit alone, but for the good of his family, to whom he did conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the Sermons. And if he found himſelf overtaken with drowſineſſe in hearing the Word (an infirmity incident to age,) his manner was to ſtand up, and to rowſe up himſelf that he might hear the more attentively; He knew that <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> conſiſted not <hi>in hearing and repetitions and Profeſſion,</hi> but in <hi>practiſe,</hi> and therefore his care was to digeſt his hearing and knowledge into an holy converſation.<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ignat. Epiſt. ad Rom.</hi> His exciting of others to good</note>
            </p>
            <p>And being <hi>deſirous not to go to heaven alone,</hi> but to draw others with him, his uſual courſe was, when he went with his family, to attend upon the Lords holy Ordinances, to give an exhortation to his children and ſervants: <hi>[that they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118215:12"/>into whoſe preſence they were going, and whom they were to hear, even that great God, to whom they were to give an account of every word which they did hear, and be careful to lay it up, for their practiſe; and not ſay, my Father or my Maſter would not afford me the time, for if they did, he would proteſt againſt them in the day of Judgment;]</hi> And as he was going to the Congregation on the Week dayes, he would often find ſome of the Country people come to the Market early in the morning, and he would ask them where they did live, and they anſwering five, or ſixe, or more miles off, be thereupon did take occaſion to ſhew them, how vain a thing it was to purſue the World, and to neglect the care of their precious ſoules, and ask them <hi>[how they could riſe ſo early to get the world, and not riſe as early to get intereſt in Jeſus Chriſt, and to attain the favour of God, and aſſurance of eternal happineſſe;]</hi> And then he would look back upon his family and ſay, <hi>[here you ſee theſe people can riſe betimes to get a little part of the world, and your will hardly ariſe early to get the aſſurance of the favour of God, which is far better then the whole world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His ſpeaking of the Serm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he heard.</note>After his return from Sermons, <hi>he would be ſpeaking</hi> to thoſe that went with him, <hi>of what they heard,</hi> exhorting them to be mindful of it, and put it in practiſe, and one of the company being troubled at the hearing of him to preſſe ſuch things upon them, told him that he had heard many good Sermons<note n="*" place="margin">The name of the Cathedral.</note> at St. <hi>Peters,</hi> but never heard one at <hi>the great Conduit</hi> before; to whom he replyed, [<hi>Sirs, are ye troubled to be put in mind of the Word of God, I pray God the time come not when you are in hell, that you wiſh you had not only practiſed the Sermons which you heard at</hi> St. Peters, <hi>but had received good counſel from the VVord at the great Conduit alſo.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Aſſurance.</note>Thus by his diligent attending upon and carefull applying the means of grace, and Gods bleſſing upon them, he attained a very great meaſure of aſſurance, a kind of <hi>Plerophory,</hi> ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of,<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 Theſſ. 1.5. <hi>much Aſſurance:</hi> and<note n="(a)" place="margin">Col. 2.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Col. 2. <hi>Full of aſſurance, of underſtanding,</hi> by which he was carried as with a full faile to holy duties: If we conſider the meaſure and the conſtancy of it, there be few Chriſtians that have attained ſo much. Aſſurance was much in his tongue and heart, and it was that which he earneſtly laboured for, and obtained by fervent prayer and diligent uſe of the means. God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118215:13"/>gave him the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 8.16.</note> 
               <hi>Teſtimony and</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Eph. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſeal of his Spirit,</hi> and ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him of his eternal love in Chriſt, of his adoption and eternal happineſſe in heaven. God gave it as part of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for his ſincere and faithful ſervice.</p>
            <p>He had ſometimes <hi>more then ordinary illapſes and incomes of the Spirit</hi> for the ſtrengthening of his aſſurance:<note place="margin">His extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</note> Ile inſtance one particular alone; He being at a Sermon, and attending heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to thoſe diſcerning and differencing marks of upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which were then laid down, and one mark being more powerfully preſſed, and coming fully home to his condition, he being in a deep and ſerious meditation, and reflecting upon himſelf, and finding it to be truly in him, it ſeemed to him, as if one ſtruck him upon the ſhoulder, incouraging him and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Be of good chear, thou art the man; upon which he had preſently ſuch inward joyes and raviſhings of Spirit as were unexpreſſible.</p>
            <p>And as he obtained, ſo he <hi>carefully kept his aſſurance</hi> by free trial of himſelf and his ſpiritual eſtate towards God;<note place="margin">His keeping his Aſſurance.</note> he had wont to try himſelf by all the marks of ſincerity which he found in the Scriptures, heard in the Miniſtry of the Word, or read in the writings of godly Divines, and thereby he did clear up his evidences for heaven; and he did not only daily try his eſtate by ſome marks, but he kept a narrow watch over his heart and wayes, and ſo his aſſurance was preſerved. And he kept it a long time together, for 30. years or more: And being asked whether he never met with any temptations of doubting of his eſtate towards God, he gave this anſwer, [That he had been and often was ſorely aſſaulted by Satans temptations, which were ſet againſt his faith and aſſurance, and that he had been foiled in reſpect of the application of ſome particular promiſes, but he was not driven from his holdfaſt of Chriſt, or from the aſſurance of his intereſt in the Covenant of grace, but ſtill he acknowledged, that his aſſurance and all his ability in ſpiritual things was <hi>through Chriſt that ſtrengthened him,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> Phil. 4.]</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His exciting others to get Aſſurance.</note>As he had this aſſurance in himſelf, ſo <hi>he was very forward to ſtir up others to get this aſſurance;</hi> there were ſcarce any that he met with, if he ſuppoſed that their faces were heavenward, but he would be queſtioning with them about their aſſurance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118215:13"/>blaming them if they did not labor for it, &amp; encouraging them to ſeek for it. And when ſome did ask him how they ſhould get it, he gave this anſwer, [<hi>That they ſhould importunately ſeek it of God, and not give him any reſt untill be granted it unto them; I would</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>lock or bolt my door, and beg it of God, and I would never give him reſt untill I had obtained it;</hi> and then, that they ſhould daily try themſelves by ſome marks, and three he did often mention as trying himſelf thereby: 1. A ſincere deſire to fear the name of God, as<note n="(e)" place="margin">Nehem. 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> Nehem. 1. 2. A ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere endeavour to do the will of God in all things required,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.6.</note> Pſal. 119. 3. A <hi>full purpoſe of heart to cleave to the Lord,</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Act. 11.23.</note> Act. 11. And theſe he did not onely ſpeak of, but preſſe with much earneſtneſſe, as longing that others ſhould partake of that high priviledge and heavenly gift with himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He feared not Death.</note>From this aſſurance it was, that he was ſo <hi>fearleſſe of death;</hi> he knew that <hi>death was an enemy,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26.</note> 1 Cor. 15. but that through Chriſt it was a friend to open the gate to heaven. Whereas death is as Bildad ſaith,<note n="(i)" place="margin">Job 18.14. <hi>N. Annot. in. loc.</hi>
               </note> Job 18. <hi>the King of terrours</hi> to fleſh and blood: and as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Ariſt. Ethic. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> on that was led by the light of Nature ſaid, That it was the moſt terrible of all terrible things; yet he being aſſured of his intereſt in Chriſt, it was not ſo to him, for he<note n="(l)" place="margin">Vid. Gryn. Diſp. Theol. de Mortis metu.</note> looked upon it as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt its ſting in Chriſt. He made it ſo familiar to him by his continual meditating of it, that he was ſo far from fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it, that he did delight in the ſpeaking of it, earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it, and with joy expected it; whereby he diſcovered his great<note n="(m)" place="margin">Calvin. Inſtit. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> § <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> proficiency in the School of Chriſt. It was his uſual ſaying, [That if death were offered on the one hand, and the Kings Crown on the other, he would take the Crown and throw it into the Kennel, and chuſe death far above the<note n="(n)" place="margin">The ſame ſpirit breathed in him, as in <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ignat. Epiſt. ad Rom.</hi>
               </note> crown;] for he knew he ſhould be a gainer by it, for he ſhould obtain the <hi>crown of life and glory,</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">He had a deſire to have dyed for Chriſt, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> of old, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Ignat. Epiſt. ad Rom.</hi>
               </note> Jam. 1. 1 Pet. 5. And that he <hi>feared not,</hi> but rather<note n="(p)" place="margin">Jam. 1.12. 1 Pet. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>hoped for death:</hi> It appears by this, that when the Plague was very hot in the City, and he being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118215:14"/>in the higheſt place of Authority there at that time, and the poor flocked about his houſe for relief, though he would not cauſeleſly expoſe himſelf to danger; yet being in the diſcharge of his duty he feared not the plague, but he often profeſſed, <hi>[That if the Plague ſhould (by Gods dispoſing) ſeize upon him, he would have kiſſed and welcom'd it as the Meſſenger of death;]</hi> Nor was the meditation of death then in his mind onely in times of danger, but at all times, there was not a day when he did not ſpeak of it; and not onely when there was occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion offered of ſuch diſcourſe, but he would take occaſion to ſpeak of it; as if he were invited to a Feaſt, he would tell the Meſſenger, <hi>[That he would come if he did live ſo long:]</hi> And when he went out of his houſe upon publick or private buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he would as it were take a ſolemn leave of his wife tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her, <hi>[That he knew not whether he ſhould return to his houſe again.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note>But <hi>his mind</hi> was not ſo much upon death <hi>as upon hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> (to which he was aſſured that death would be a paſſage for him) ſure his heart was much in heaven, or heaven was much in his heart, as appears by his frequent diſcourſe of it both day and night; for<note n="(q)" place="margin">Matth. 12.34.</note> Matth. 12. <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh:</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">As <hi>Ignatius</hi> of old had the name of Jeſus ſo deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in his heart, that he could not but make frequent mention of it, <hi>H. Magd. Cent.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> All that knew him (and looked upon him with an unprejudic'd eye) would ſay, that he was a moſt heavenly minded man, a man that lived as much in heaven, as moſt that ever lived upon the earth: When in the night he looked upon thoſe <hi>bright lights of heaven,</hi>
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Ezek. 32.8.</note> Ezek. 32. the firmament adorned with thoſe <hi>ſtars of light,</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 148 3.</note> Pſal. 148. he had wont to raiſe up his thoughts and his ſpeech much higher, to the glory of the higheſt heaven, ſaying, <hi>[If this heaven be ſo glorious, how doth the heaven above exceed in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where God alone ſhall be the light; and yet the righteous ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father,]</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Matth. 13.43.</note> Matth. 13. Theſe are but ſome few heads of his Piety, to which much more may be added, and they that knew him will mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, not that ſo much is ſaid, but that no more.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. He was <hi>as eminent for Juſtice, as for Piety;</hi> when he was advanced to the chiefeſt place of Government in the City,<note place="margin">His Juſtice.</note> to be the<note n="*" place="margin">A. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1617.</note> 
               <hi>Major of that Honourable Corporation,</hi> he was an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118215:14"/>Magiſtrate,</hi> not only in the year of his Majoralty, but ever after ſo long as he lived; he looked not upon it as a <hi>place of honour</hi> onely, but as <hi>an office of truſt,</hi> wherein he might honour God, and do Juſtice to men, and reform thoſe evills which abounded then in that place: He did not glory ſo much in having the Sword carried before him, (though it were a ſingular honour to that City,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh.</note> that the <hi>Kings Sword</hi> ſhould be taken from his ſide and delivered to the Major to be carried before him, as a ſignal teſtimony of his favour, and their loyalty and courage in the inſurrection of <hi>Perkin War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck.</hi>) as he was deſirous to draw forth the <hi>ſword of</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtice againſt evil doers, and not to hold it in vain,</hi> Rom. 13.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His impartial adminiſtring of Juſtice.</note>He was obſerved to be one that did impartially adminiſter Juſtice, and without reſpect of Perſons did puniſh evil doers, of what quality or condition ſoever they were that did tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the Law; whether they were of the City, or ſtrangers that came thither, they ſhould not (if complaint were made to him) eſcape condigne puniſhment, ſuch as the Lawes of the Land, or cuſtome of the place did award.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An inſtance of it.</note>To give but one inſtance of many; there was a <hi>Gentleman of quality</hi> (whoſe name I ſpare) that was complained of for ſwearing five Oathes, and other miſdemeanors, thereupon Mr. <hi>Jurdain</hi> ſent a Conſtable with a Warrant to bring him before him, but the Gentleman gave the Conſtable mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing termes, ſo that he durſt not execute his office, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon M. <hi>Jurdain</hi> ſent one Conſtable more, who brought the Gentleman to him, and he being in his Court when he came, after divers good admonitions given him, and telling him, that though he were never ſo great a Gentleman, <hi>[That he could no more go to heaven ſo long as he took ſuch courſes, than he could eat that ſtone,]</hi> (pointing to a great ſtone in his Court) he required him to pay five ſhillings for ſwearing, which he did, as alſo to give in ſureties for his good behaviour; but this the Gentleman refuſed to do, ſaying, he was a ſtranger; thereupon Mr. <hi>Jurdain</hi> bad the Conſtables to carry him away to priſon, till he ſhould find ſureties, which they did, and as he was going into the priſon door, he deſired to return back again, and he would give baite, which he did; and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118215:15"/>received many good inſtructions, (though he were a man of a very high ſpirit) gave him many hearty thanks, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of amendment for the future.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bridewell</hi> could witneſſe how many diſorderly perſons were ſent thither by his Warrants, more then any other of the Juſtices of his time.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Stocks and whipping Poſts</hi> could teſtifie, what Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Drunkards, unclean Perſons, and ſuch like notorious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders were puniſhed principally by his executing of Juſtice. And if any of the Offenders, that were liable to the cenſure and penalty of the Law, deſired to be ſpared, he would tell them, <hi>[Here be my Children whom I dearly love, and if any of them ſhould commit ſuch offences, they ſhould ſuffer as you muſt do, and therefore I cannot remit of the penalty of the Law.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How fair pretences ſoever they made, he cauſed the Law to be executed on them; yea and the more ſeverely becauſe of the greater diſhonour that redounded to the name of the holy God thereby.</p>
            <p>When ſome ſcandalous Offenders, (whoſe names I omit) for the groſſe ſin of Uncleanneſſe were accuſed and queſtioned before the Court, and ſome for by-reſpects did plead for them to have them ſpared, he deſired that the Watchmen that were at the Gates to keep out the Plague (it being a time that the ſickneſſe was in ſome neighbouring Townes) ſhould be called home, <hi>for the Plague was in the Guild-Hall of the City;</hi> and he told them, that <hi>if they did not execute the Law upon them, he would complain of them to the Councel Table;</hi> and thereupon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter much conteſt, there was order taken for their ſevere and juſt puniſhment.</p>
            <p>He was <hi>very vigilant</hi> (eſpecially in his Majoralty, when the Government of the City lay moſt upon him) both to <hi>prevent and remove diſorders,</hi> ſo that he would go with the Conſtables in Perſon to ſearch for idle and diſorderly perſons on Sabbath dayes at night, and at the end of the Aſſizes and Seſſions, and Fair weeks.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Zeal againſt Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>He did not onely <hi>execute Juſtice,</hi> but he ſhewed himſelf very <hi>zealous therein,</hi> and the greateſt indignation againſt thoſe evils whereby God was moſt highly diſhonoured, as <hi>ſwearing</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118215:15"/>and <hi>Sabbath-breaking;</hi> ſwearing was moſt odious to him; and had there been a greater penalty then was at that time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Law of the Land, he would moſt gladly have inflicted it. But he puniſhing as many as were brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, ſtruck ſuch an awe into moſt, that ſome that lived then in the City, and near the place of the greateſt concourſe of people, the Corn-Market, obſerved, that they did not hear an oath ſworn for many years together.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it.</note>I have heard it credibly related, that being ſummoned to appear at the Star-Chamber, for an act of Juſtice, wherein it was ſuppoſed that he went ſomewhat beyond the ſtrict letter of the Law, (of which I ſhall hereafter give an account) and being in the preſence of ſome of his Judges, and hearing them to ſwear divers oaths, he told them, <hi>That they muſt pay for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry oath that they had ſworn, or otherwiſe he would make it farther known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Againſt the Profaning of the Sabbath.</note>When he was <hi>Major,</hi> he did much <hi>reform the open profaning of the Sabbath;</hi> for whereas the Fullers had wont to ſet their Mills a going on the Sabbath, he put a ſtop upon them for that whole day, knowing that that day was fully to be dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to God and his worſhip and ſervice; and whereas it was uſual to ſell fruit and herbs, and other things on the Lords holy day, and Bowling and Cudgel-playing, and other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane paſtimes were then much uſed, by his zeal and vigilancy, and the care of good Officers under him, they were wholly removed, though not without much reluctancy and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and<note n="(x)" place="margin">He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with unreaſonable men, as <hi>Paul</hi> with beaſts at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.32. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and as <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martye from <hi>Syria</hi> to <hi>Rome. Ignat. Epiſt. ad Rom. &amp; Epiſt. ad Tarſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> danger at the firſt; for there were Commotions and Tumults, and great reſiſtance, but by his conſtant zeal for God and his day, they were ſuppreſſed and quel'd.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">His Conſtancy in the execution of Juſtice.</note>And not onely when he was Major, but ever after being a Juſtice of Peace; And he continued ſo for 22. years: he was much employed in the execution of Juſtice, ſometimes the whole day from morning to night; he did not only exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cute Judgment in the<note n="(y)" place="margin">Jer. 21.12.</note> morning (after he had been with God in the mount of heavenly meditation) but all the day
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118215:16"/>long; <hi>as Moſes ſate to judge the people, and the people ſtood before Moſes from Morning to the Evening,</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Exod 18.13. His Mercy in Judgment.</note> Exod. 18.</p>
            <p>He was not for <hi>Judgment</hi> onely, but for <hi>Mercy</hi> alſo, and he ſhewed mercy to the ſoules of thoſe that were brought before him as tranſgreſſors of the Law, and to be puniſhed according to the Law, for he would labour to convince them of the hainouſneſſe of their offences, that he might bring them to the ſight of their ſins, and to repentance for them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</note>He did much encourage the Officers under him to the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and faithful diſcharge of their duy; (and they ſtood in need of it, meeting with much diſcouragement from ſome others) and finding them ſomewhat backward, through timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe or other by-reſpects, to execute his Warrants upon men of high place, he would encourage them to be active and forward in doing their duty, and tell them in good earneſt, (for that was his uſual word) <hi>That if he had as good a Warrant from God, as they had from him to apprehend offenders, if he were required to apprehend the devil himſelf, he would not be backward to put it in execution.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. He was not more famous for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> then for <hi>Charity,</hi> both in his life,<note place="margin">His Charity.</note> and at his death: In his life-time he was a man free-hearted, and open-handed, he was a great friend and Patron of the poor; he was another <hi>Job</hi> in that reſpect, he could truly ſay with him,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Job 30.25.</note> Job 30. <hi>Was not my ſoul grieved for the poor?</hi> it was no doubt; and the bowels of his compaſſion did yearn towards them; he was an <hi>Advocate,</hi> and did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly plead for them, and eſpecially for <hi>Gods poor,</hi> honeſt poor men, whoſe hearts and faces were ſet Godward and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venward, and his hands were very open to relieve them; he did that for them which few others of far greater eſtate had hearts to do.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His care for the Poor in the time of the Plague. <hi>A. C.</hi> 1625</note>His Care for the poor was moſt remarkable in the time of the great Plague in the City (which was 28. years ſince;) for, in the Majors abſence being choſen his Deputy or Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, he ſeeing the deplored condition of the City, accepted of it: And then he wrote divers Letters to many Townes in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and ſome in <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and <hi>Sommerſetſhire,</hi> and by that means procured divers ſummes of Moneyes, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Wants of the many hundreds of poor that at that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118215:16"/>time were in a very diſtreſſed condition; I have it from the relation of one that was a neer neighbour, and diligent obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of his care for the publick good of the City and for the poor, that he had ſeen morning after morning coming to his door ſometimes thirty, ſometimes fourty, fifty, or threeſcore, or more; ſome wringing their hands, and crying that their husbands were dead; others that their wives were dead, others that their children were dead, and that they had not any thing to bury them: Some again, that their Families were ſick, and they had not wherewithal to relieve them: Others, that they had divers Children, but they had no bread, nor money to buy it for them; ſome cryed for bread, ſome for Phyſick, ſome for ſhrouds. And he not onely gave them the hearing, but <hi>his bowels yerned</hi> towards them, and <hi>his hands were ſtretched out</hi> for their relief: For, ſtanding within his Shop. With his own hands he gave ſupplies unto them all, and ſent them to their homes for the preſent; and then the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was a renewing of the ſad complaints of the poor, and his renewing of his charitable care of them, and ſo Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Morning for near three moneths, untill the Major came into the City.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His care for poor Houſe-keepers.</note>Beſides his great care to ſupply the wants of the poor that came unto him, he had a <hi>ſpecial respect to poor Houſe-keepers and Tradeſmen,</hi> ſuch as were aſhamed or unwilling to make their poor and ſad condition known, and a peculiar care of the Godly poor, concerning whom, he would adviſe with the Conſtables and Church-Wardens of every Pariſh, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their need would proportion ſome relief and help unto them, and ſend it by the hands of the Conſtables or Wardens.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His conſtant care for the poor.</note>And his care for the poor was not onely very great at that extraordinary ſeaſon, (as their exigents did require) but ſo long as he continued in the Land of the living; and he was ſo <hi>conſtantly verſed</hi> in this great <hi>work of Charity,</hi> that he did it as it were <hi>naturally,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Phil. 2.20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Phil. 2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An Aſperſion caſt upon him wip'd off.</note>But though he did <hi>well,</hi> yet he <hi>heard ill</hi> for this, and it was by ſome caſt in his teeth that he made beggars: And when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118215:17"/>he was asked by a man of place and eſtate, what he would give to keep the poor from begging; (ſuppoſing that he would not be ſo forward therein as he was in relieving them) he freely offered a great part of his eſtate, on condition that the other would do the like; but he could not obtain that of him to follow him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note>He was <hi>given much to Hospitality,</hi> he did <hi>not love to eat his morſels alone by himſelf,</hi> as<note n="(c)" place="margin">Job 31.17.</note> Job 31. he did well remember the Apoſtles direction,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 13.2.</note> Heb. 13. <hi>Be not forgetful to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſtrangers,</hi> he was moſt loving and friendly to them, and ſuch eſpecially as did <hi>ſuffer for their conſcience ſake;</hi> as thoſe godly Miniſters that were ſilenced for Non-conformity (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his judgment was in a good meaſure ſatisfied in that point) to him they did continually reſort, and by him were kindly entertained; So that by the profaner ſort, he was cryed out upon as the Arch-Puritan; and by thoſe that took Religion to heart, honoured with the title of <hi>Gaius mine hoſte, and of the whole Church,</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 16.23.</hi> N. Annot. in loc.</note> Rom. 16. And he is much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his hoſpitality, (if it be the ſame <hi>Gaius</hi> as it ſeems to be)<note n="(f)" place="margin">3 Joh. 5, 6.</note> 3 Joh. 5.6. <hi>Beloved thou doeſt faithfully, whatſoever thou doeſt to the brethren</hi> (thy neighbour Chriſtians) <hi>and to ſtrangers which have born witneſſe of thy charity before the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Legacies in his Will.</note>But if we conſider <hi>his laſt Will or Teſtament,</hi> we ſhall ſee very rare and unparallel'd acts of Charity: As he gave one third part of his temporal eſtate to his Wife, and another third part to his Children; (according to the cuſtome of the City) ſo out of the other third part he left very large Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, eſpecially to the poor: I ſhall omit many Legacies given to Miniſters and others, and point at ſome more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable; I will deliver it in the words of his Will, <hi>[Firſt I give to all the poor of this City and County that have pay of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, and alſo thoſe which dwell in</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">There were ſeven or eight of them.</note> 
               <hi>Almes-houſes, I give five ſhillings to each to be paid at my burial; I give to one hundred poor people more ten ſhillings to each, to be given to ſuch as my Overſeers ſhall think to have moſt need, the honeſt poor to be chiefly looked unto. Alſo I give to the poor of</hi> Lyme <hi>where I was born, and to the poor of</hi> Garnſey <hi>where I was new-born, five pounds to each place:</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118215:17"/>(which accordingly was done by thoſe Overſeers) <hi>Alſo I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all the moneys owing to me, if it be under the</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Theſe ſmaller ſums to the poor were very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> 
               <hi>value of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhillings each.]</hi> And after in a Poſtſcript <hi>[Alſo my Will is, and I give now more to fifty poor people of this City and County, by twenty ſhillings to each by my Overſeers, or moſt part of them.]</hi> Thus out of that eſtate which God had given him, he gave again by way of gratitude to God, I mean to the poor, who are Gods Receivers: God gave him and left him a competent eſtate, (after his many and great loſſes) and which was more, he gave him an heart <hi>to honour</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Prov. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>him with his ſubſtance,</hi> and to lay it forth as it became a faithful Steward, in the ſervice and for the honour of his Lord who had intruſted him with it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Apology for his Charity.</note>I know that ſome do <hi>wonder,</hi> and others <hi>ſharply cenſure</hi> him for his <hi>extraordinary charity</hi> and liberality, and eſpecially for that he left no greater portion of his eſtate to his Wife; but this may be ſaid in his defence, That the ſtreight and <hi>cloſe hearts</hi> of men are not a fit meaſure to meaſure his <hi>large heart</hi> by: And beſides, God had opened his hand, and given very liberally to him bleſſings ſpiritual and temporal; and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſpiritual, the graces and comforts of his Spirit: and he having ſo ſweet a Communion with God above moſt other men, what mervail if he did more for God then other men? And concerning his Wife, as he left her the third part of his eſtate, ſo likewiſe Executrix of his Will, and there had much more come unto her then did, had not ſome debts (which he accounted good) failed and come ſhort of his and her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation: beſides, he did aſſure himſelf, that her<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Simon Baskervill.</note> Brother then living, a man of great eſtate, would be ready to ſupply any of her wants.</p>
            <p>Thus you have ſeen <hi>what he did for God;</hi> and we are next to conſider <hi>what God did for him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">What God did for him.</note> Beſides all thoſe graces which were eminently in him, whereby he was enabled to act ſo zealouſly and vigorouſly for God, which were the free gift of God, and that Aſſurance which he had, which was a part of his reward; The Lord <hi>advanced</hi> him from a mean and low eſtate, to <hi>the higheſt place of dignity</hi> in the City; his beginning was but ſmall, as appears by his anſwer to thoſe that threatned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118215:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>to follow him with Suits, that they would not leave him worth a groat; he chearfully replied, [<hi>That he ſhould be then but two pence poorer then when he came firſt to</hi> Exeter, <hi>for he brought but ſix pence with him thither:</hi>] And yet, by Gods bleſſing on his labours, he got a competent and comfortable eſtate, whereby he did maintain a large Family of Children and Servants, kept hoſpitality, was liberal to the poor, and open-handed to any pious uſe, more then thoſe that had far greater eſtates: but when he had the greateſt temporal eſtate, he ſet no high eſtimate upon theſe fading periſhing things, he ſet them not up in his heart (as the men of the World uſe to do) but trod them under his feet; and he did uſually ſet them very low in his ordinary diſcourſe, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when he was ſpeaking of heaven and heavenly things: And yet he did not forget to acknowledge Gods goodneſſe in beſtowing any of theſe outward things upon him; He found by experience the <hi>uncertainty of riches,</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note> 1 Tim. 6. and <hi>that they had wings and would fly away,</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> Prov. 23. but he did not run after them, crying, as they that uſe to ſet their hearts upon them, but ſaw <hi>Gods</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Job 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>hand in taking as in giving,</hi> and ſo was quiet and content, having experimentally learned in a good meaſure that great and difficult <hi>leſſon, to be content in any eſtate,</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">Phil. 4.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Phil. 4. by viciſſitudes and changes of eſtates God did exerciſe his faith and patience, and Contentation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Majoralty.</note>Having paſſed through the ſeveral Offices, he aſcended at laſt to the higheſt place of honour in the City, to be <hi>Major</hi> there, wherein (as hath been ſaid) he demeaned himſelf as it became a <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate,</hi> and his ambition therein was highly to honour God who had honoured him. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he was choſen to be a Burgeſſe for the Parliament,<note place="margin">Burgeſſe of Parliament.</note> wherein his zeal for God, and againſt the corruptions of the times was abundantly manifeſted. He was a great ſtickler to have the Bill paſſed for the puniſhment of Adultery with death; but thoſe times would not bear it, ſome of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers knew ſome ſpecial reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His honour in the hearts of Good men.</note>God did not only advance him to places of dignity and honour in the eye of the world, but gave him an <hi>high place in the hearts of his people;</hi> and if it be true which the<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſt. Ethic. l.</hi> 1.6.5.</note> 
               <hi>Moraliſt</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118215:18"/>notes, that honour is in the Perſon honouring; then he being advanced in the hearts of men, (as he was eſpecially in the hearts of good men) he was highly honoured, and therein God made good his promiſe to him,<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> 1 Sam. 2. <hi>Such as honour me I will honour.</hi> And his name was very precious in the ſight of thoſe that knew his worth, while he lived, and ſince his death.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge that he was <hi>a by-word</hi> to many,<note place="margin">A by-word to Others.</note> and that his name was taken up by way of reproach, but they were ſuch as were upbraided, and reproved by his holy and gracious converſation, and reproved by his holy and gracious conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and he knew that his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> did ſuffer much more in this kind, that this was a <hi>chip of that croſſe</hi> which he muſt and was willing to bear, and he was well content <hi>to drink of this bitter cup after his Maſter,</hi> and with him <hi>he did deſpiſe that ſhame</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note> which the men of the world caſt upon him, nay accounted it his <hi>honour to ſuffer ſhame for the name of Chriſt,</hi> as the Apoſtles did,<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Act. 5.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Act. 5. But ſome brought ſhame upon themſelves, that thought to caſt contempt and ſcorn upon him: Among other inſtances this one was remarkable, That being choſen Burgeſſe for the Parliament, not without much oppoſition, and going up to <hi>London</hi> to clear his Election, at which time there was an accuſation ſent up againſt him by a man of no mean place and power, That he was the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſpes Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticorum.</hi> The very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in the Letter.</note> 
               <hi>hoſt of the Schiſmaticks.</hi> It was preſumed by ſome that he would be ſent back with diſgrace. And therefore there was a Sermon prepared by one to jeer him at his return, this being the text,<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 114.5</note> Pſal. 114.5. <hi>What ailed thee—thou Jordan, that thou waſt driven back?</hi> (Thus men of profane ſpirits will dare to make the Sacred Word of God to ſerve their own baſe ends and luſts,) but Mr. <hi>Jurdain</hi> was confirmed in his place to which he was choſen; and ſo ſhame was caſt into the face of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſcorner, and the <hi>Sermon,</hi> or invective rather, became <hi>abortive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">God ſtanding by him in his troubles.</note>And as he ſtood up for God, ſo <hi>God did ſtand by him,</hi> and aſſiſt him, and carry him through many troubles and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that did threaten, and even compaſſe him about. One act of Gods Providence among others was moſt notable, in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118215:19"/>delivering him out of his troubles. He having done an act of Juſtice in puniſhing an unclean Perſon (whoſe offence was aggravated by ſome heinous circumſtances) being moved with indignation againſt the offence, he went (it ſeems) beſides the Letter of the Law in ſome circumſtance. And thereupon ſome friends of the Perſon puniſhed (being ſtirred up with indignation for the diſgrace that reflected upon them, more then for the diſhonour done to God, and the foul blot that was caſt upon Religion) did reſolve to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute him to the uttermoſt for it, and they put him to great charge and trouble. When the matter came to a final deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Star-Chamber, it was much feared by many of his friends, and through the boaſting of his Adverſaries, that ſome heavy cenſure ſhould have been paſſed upon him to his cruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and undoing; and when friends failed him on earth, he flees to heaven for ſuccour and defence, he cryed to God in <hi>Davids</hi> words,<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 22.11. Verſ. 19.</note> Pſal. 22. <hi>Be not far from me, O Lord, for trouble is neer, for there is none to help; and O my ſtrength, haſte thou to help me:</hi> And he ſet apart an Evening, and a great part of the night, for <hi>faſting and Prayer,</hi> that he might <hi>engage God on his ſide,</hi> who had the <hi>hearts of all men,</hi> even <hi>the greateſt in his hand to turn them as he pleaſed,</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Prov. 21.1.</note> Prov. 21. And behold the next morning <hi>a real and gracious anſwer</hi> from heaven, he was acquitted and commended by the Lord Keeper, and God ſtirred up the hearts of divers of that high Arbitrary Court to ſpeak in his behalf; <hi>Thus the Lord was a very preſent help in trouble to him,</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſal. 46.1.</note> Pſal. 46. And after that he was freed and came home, he piled up the books and papers of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in that vexatious buſineſſe, under his Cupboard in his Parlour, which was the place to which he did uſually reſort: (and where he had that daily ſweet heavenly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God forementioned.) And being asked the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why he left ſo many papers and books to lye in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; his anſwer was, <hi>[Theſe I keep in my ſight as memorials and Monuments of Gods mercy in freeing me from my troubles.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the principal things that came within mine obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, or notice from others that well knew this Saint of God, ſo <hi>eminent for Piety, Juſtice, and Charity,</hi> and zealous in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118215:19"/>all, in the general courſe of his converſation: Many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars have been omitted, but by that little which hath been ſaid, you may<note n="(y)" place="margin">Ex pede Herculem. A. Gell. Noct. Att. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1. His Sickneſſe.</hi>
               </note> gheſſe at the great worth of this holy man.</p>
            <p>I come now to the laſt <hi>act of his life, his ſickneſſe, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of that, his death:</hi> In his ſickneſſe which was very painful, he being ſorely afflicted with the Stone and the Cholick, he manifeſted more then ordinary Patience,<note place="margin">His patience.</note> not opening his mouth in any word that might ſavour of any repining or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content at his preſent condition, but meekly and patiently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to Gods afflicting hand, and waiting for his long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected and deſired diſſolution:<note place="margin">His Faith and Aſſurance.</note> He did then much <hi>act faith in Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his gracious Promiſes, and his <hi>aſſurance remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unſhaken,</hi> though Satan was then buſie with him by his temptations; but <hi>being ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</hi> he did reſiſt him: Some of his neareſt friends, that obſerved his confident aſſurance in the courſe of his life, of his happy eſtate in heaven after death, did ſuppoſe that Satan would have ſet upon him with ſo much violence as to have ſhaken his aſſurance, and, no doubt, he had will enough to do it, but God, who had him in his chain, would not permit him to do it; but he went out of the world as a <hi>Conquerour</hi> out of the field, being victorious through Chriſt over all his ſpiritual enemies. I may not omit one particular in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which was, his taking all occaſions of exhorting and encouraging others to conſtancy in the faith,<note place="margin">His Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to others.</note> zeal for God, and making ſure of heaven; and his ſpirits beginning to fail him, he would ſay, <hi>[I cannot speak much more to you now, remember what you have heard from me in my health;]</hi> And he was willing to <hi>incite others</hi> that were abſent to the diſcharge of their duties; He inſtance onely one particular, that the <hi>Major of the City,</hi> that then was, ſending to viſit him, he called the Meſſenger unto him, and ſaid <hi>[Remember me to Mr. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, and tell him from me, that he have a ſpecial care of theſe three things; To do Juſtice, to provide carefully for the poor, and to make ſure of heaven;]</hi> His gracious ſpeeches in the time of his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe were many, and more then I can, or were fit here to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">His Death.</note>Having <hi>fought the good fight of faith and finiſhed his courſe,</hi> he
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118215:20"/>ſweetly and quietly reſigned up his ſoul into the hands of his bleſſed Saviour and Redeemer; He departed this life July 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.<note place="margin">On the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</note> 1640. being the Chriſtian Sabbath, <hi>The Sabbath was his delight</hi> on earth, and on that day God gave him to enjoy an <hi>Eternal Sabbath</hi> with him in heaven: As he had ſweet <hi>Communion</hi> with God in the uſe of <hi>Ordinances</hi> for many years on that day, ſo he went to enjoy an <hi>immediate Communion</hi> with God on that holy day: And <hi>after all his labours he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into reſt, that glorious reſt in heaven,</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Heb. 4.11.</note> Heb. 4. His depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hence was in the 79.<note place="margin">His Age.</note> year of his age and, according to his account for the new birth, in the 65<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. year, for ſo long he reckoned ſince the time of his effectual Calling.<note place="margin">His Funeral.</note> His <hi>Funeral</hi> being kept ſome few daies after, there hath not been any man known to be <hi>more lamented</hi> then he, the loſſe being ſo great not to the City alone, but to all theſe Weſtern parts, the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of his example</hi> as a zealous Magiſtrate and Chriſtian <hi>reaching far and neer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude this Story of his Life and Death with that which was the text of his Funeral Sermon,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Act. 13.36.</note> (Omitting only the name of <hi>David</hi>) Act. 13. <hi>After he had ſerved his own gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by the will of God he fell on ſleep;</hi> He ſleeps in the Lord, and <hi>will riſe gloriouſly in the Morning of the Reſurrection,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Pſal. 17. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> Pſal. 17. and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Pſal. 49.14.</note> Pſal. 49.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Being dead he yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note>But though he ſleeps the ſleep of death, yet, <hi>being dead</hi> with <hi>Abel he yet speaketh,</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> Heb. 11. His zealous converſation ſpeaketh zeal and fervency to this <hi>Laodicean</hi> and luke-warm generation, and beſpeaks all Chriſtian Magiſtrates, eſpecially thoſe of that City where he lived, and all the Saints in all places to imitate his Piety, Juſtice, Charity, and all thoſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which did ſhine forth in his holy and gracious converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Ile ſhut up all with that voyce from Heaven, Revel. 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118215:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
